howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talked
about on the show we now have links to
books and articles referenced in recent
podcasts that are available on our
website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com
that's Jim ruts show com today's guest
is Mark Burgess an independent
researcher and writer hey Jim thanks for
having me back yeah it's great to have
you back on our first episode was so
interesting I figured Dan must find out
what he knows about money the other
thing he's written about mark is a
theoretical physicist by training he's
also a technologist scientist in various
domains an advisor to public and private
organizations globally he's also what I
might call a practical philosopher with
his development of promise theory and
yeah he writes fiction and composes
music today we're going to examine
another of his interests money mark has
written a very interesting book on the
topic money ownership an agency is an
application of promise theory as always
we'll have a link to it unmarked episode
page at jib rut comm check it out the
foundation of your work on money is your
earlier work on promise theory could you
very briefly outline promise theory for
our audience
sure promise theory is really a way of
modeling stuff that happens and in a way
that tries to build systems from the
bottom up so you you look at the
smallest pieces of a system and then try
to see how they compose to to create the
whole and you do it by basically
breaking everything down into a bunch of
agents agents can be people things
machines mineral animal vegetable
whatever and and the promises they make
to one another the promises are
statements of intent or or alignment of
intent and by creating that network
between agents of the intent and the
direction in which they're moving you
hope to model systems and their outcomes
so I guess that's a short
and that's great they're really very
rich theory and we talk about it
considerably more detailed in ep 28
where mark was the guest on the Jim
Rutte show so just type in mark Burgess
EP 28 Jim rut show into Google and you
will find it let's now jump into money
very big picture in your mind mark what
is money for I like that picture jumping
into money I could I could do that could
do that all day
what is money for I think money is for
communicating intent in a sense but it's
steeper than that because money is not
an expression of intent and in the
normal way that we think of money at
least in the in the modern version of
money that were used to using it's it's
at a layer below that which is a more of
a transport mechanism on top of which
intentions ride but it's some a medium
of exchange you know and whenever you
have exchanges you have people
interacting over a length of time and
building up a relationship with one
another and so money has this important
role in our society of maintaining
relationships even when perhaps we don't
communicate by talking on the phone or
visit one another for dinner so much
anymore as long as we're sending little
packets of money back and forth we still
have a relationship going so it becomes
a proxy for maintaining relationships
and therefore trusts very good the first
thing I learned reading your book that
caused me to raise my eyebrows I hear
something I hadn't thought up quite like
this before as you described money as a
network transfer system very clever
insight did you tell us more about that
yeah so having money as a go-between and
exchanges has a lot of advantages right
so you know some writers claim that
barter preceded money in in some version
of history and others I think
convincingly argue that that was enough
there was never really a time on which
money wasn't used in some sense and and
if we get when we get into promise there
you can explain that bartered goods are
really
kind of private currency by looking at
the patterns that are that it represents
like almost like a one-time pad but um
you know barter was the way that we
started to exchange things in the past
when you had a certain kind of good that
you wanted to sell me a bunch of wheat
and I'd give you back a bunch of wood or
or honey or whatever it was and we would
make these exchanges with much more
personal contact than than in the past
but then as time went by trade you know
expanded became more global there was
the Silk Road and the the Islamic empire
spread its wings or its donkeys or
camels across the the world and and
trade really took on a global dimension
where you didn't really want to be
carrying tons of wheats or camels or or
honey around the world to exchange
things if you could get away with it if
you if you took something in one
direction it would be nice just to have
a monetary note to give in return to say
okay you owe me something in return you
don't have to give it to me right now
but we will make a note of that and we
will settle up later on and so that roll
information in a virtual sense of
informations rather than a physical
representation of information started to
enter into the dialogue of that was that
with trade and that's really where the
networking concept began having money as
you know go-between has a lot of
advantages because it has no opinion no
affinity to a particular thing you know
wheat or honey or anything like that and
then it also allows us to maintain a
clean separation between entities if you
like a kind of locality of
decision-making which sometimes is
desirable sometimes it isn't but you
know it's desirable if you want to think
of private property and incentives
within society for fun or profit so you
know money begins as this kind of
virtual communicating device to settle
the tray
but then it takes on this new
information dimension and Trust building
context and can even become a motivation
in its own right to hold a lot of this
stuff gives you a lot of mobility
because you can exchange one good for
another it's fungible it doesn't even
require me to get something back from
you you know if we if you give me
something I don't have to give you
something back I could give somebody
else something and they could give you
something so there's this it extends and
expands the the network dimensions if
you will of exchanges and trades in a
way that we now understand networks to
do yep and it also allowed much longer
range trade right particularly when
money started become denser like gold or
even better in book entries like the
northern Italian bankers in the 13th
century trade networks could now be
linked by these money signals from
northern Italy to the Netherlands and
back at the rate of horseback or sailing
ship but certainly much quicker than
having to haul a vast wad of wheat from
Genoa to Rotterdam yeah exactly and the
one that I like is we still use the name
check from from the French root of the
Persian word sharafa King which was
basically by the order of the king we
would have these money orders or
promissory notes that could be sent back
and forth or rather than a train of
camels to to carry gold or whatever but
this use of this gold is interesting as
well because you begin with bulk amounts
of things like wheat and and similar
substances which which are enormous
volumes heavy weights and difficult to
transport but then you you have things
like gold and silver which are precious
substances with the very small weight
you consider them to be worth very much
more and so you can keep a little a few
coins of gold in your pocket and buy a
huge bunch of wheat much easier to carry
around but still problematic because the
the gold still has intrinsic value so
it's still a bit risky to carry it
around and then we go all the way to
some
paper checks and promissory notes and
the paper money and the valueless coins
that were later invented to avoid things
like coin clipping which allow you to
totally separate the function of
remembering debts if you will
remembering how to settle up to an
accounting brick as you would having a
game board from the actual valuable
thing itself which which is much more
risky and difficult to carry around
yep that's absolutely true you talked
about medium of exchange as one of the
features that money has and historically
it's described as having three features
medium of exchange to where value and
numeraire a measure of value let's talk
a little bit about store of value one of
the other interesting things that the
emergence of money provides I'd love to
get your perspective on this is to store
value and in fact if we then lay that on
to your concept of network we might be
able to think of money something like a
capacitor in the network it allows us to
store some amount of our energy
quote-unquote for some period of time
because it may be that I'm willing to
you know sell my wheat today but I don't
really want to buy some bread until
Tuesday and having money in between lets
me easily and at lower risk essentially
store that energy for some period of
time and of course while it probably
started out as short-term storage over
time the amount of storage has tended to
increase so now we have not just
capacitors but probably batteries as
well yeah I like the picture of a
capacitor is a store you know there's an
a sociology of money as well as as a
network any network has a kind of social
function of course when the agents are
independent things each makes up its own
decision unlike an electric circuit in a
capacitor where you have something
driving the next part and it's all kind
of quasi deterministic but when you have
agents that are acting independently
more like a bunch of cells then the
dynamics of that Network are a little
bit different
so by holding money you're you're trying
to separate the notion of a fair
exchange and measuring that fair
exchange on some scale
what we now idolize is the concept of
value which is a kind of proxy for
fairness you know where we fare in our
transactions you know from the actual
functional things that money does the
exchange details of it and money you
know it's not supposed to have an
intrinsic purpose it's just a memory or
accounting like this game brick that I
was talking about but what's interesting
is when you have this way of counting
you can then accumulate these counters
as you say and it becomes a kind of a
store a trusted store and that allows us
to play a game with time in the way that
capacitors and other stores of energy
allow us to do in the physical world if
we build up a store of something we can
then use it all in one go so by saving
up a pile of money we can afford
something that we wouldn't be able to
afford given the rate of our normal
earnings or if we come into some sudden
wealth where we can we can spin that out
out over a longer period of time and
survive for you know a longer period of
time so it has a buffering capacity as
you as you described which is pretty
important because there are many things
in the world that we simply can't afford
to do we don't have enough resources to
to climb over a wall you know here and
you're stuck in prison if you have a
bunch of money you might be able to
bribe your way out or if you have a
bunch of energy you might be able to
leap across the wall and overcome that
potential energy with your rocket suit
and then escape captivity so this
ability to play with resources have to
build up reserve and then to use it in a
sudden amounts or sudden burst allows us
to play with space and time as a
physicist that that appeals to me and of
course it comes back in subjects like
quantum mechanics as well but this
ability to play with time allows us to
achieve some things that which would
simply be impossible in the normal world
of agents in their normal time rates and
spatial rates
so I think it money has this important
function which has enabled a new level
of society to take place where we can
build these amazing buildings and create
cities and buy houses and do things that
would simply be impossible by normal
work sounds good next you know if we
think of money itself being a buffer
there's another very interesting kind of
elastic aspect to money that became
accreted on some people would say from
the beginning if you believe David
Graeber and that's money and debt you
talk a little bit about both the nature
of the relationship between money and
debt and their asymmetry yeah this is
something which I thought was really
nice in promise Theory you know when I
started this I I didn't know too much
about money I read pretty much
everything I could find one side finally
the bug had finally bitten me and I read
David Grady's book excellent book that
the first 5000 years for our avid
readers what promise theory kind of
shows is that money and debt are not
exact inverses of one another there's
another great book by moravsky which is
called more heat than light and he
describes the history of economics I
suppose money can money in economics in
the 20th century actually from the 18th
century through the 20th century and
describes how economists were had this
kind of they were very enamored by
physics they had physics Envy as many
subjects do because physicists had been
so successful in describing the world by
in terms of laws and rules and could
perform these marvelous calculations to
predict the future and everyone wanted
that for for money and there was an
obvious analogy between money and energy
energy is basically an accounting
parameter in calculations about momentum
and motion in the Newtonian formulation
of physics and so people saw this
connection between money or this analogy
fuel between money and energy and they
wanted that for
anomic so they started to create these
theories based around that and one of
the ideas that you have in energy is
that energy is conserved
you know once created it's never
destroyed but if you create energies as
you sometimes can in quantum processes
you create an anti an anti version that
is well you create matter and antimatter
and then if they are ever destroyed they
would turn back into energy so that the
accounting is never broken or the you
know you never lose track of anything as
you're not supposed to in money either
we should say but so this is interesting
because of course there's no reason why
money should be conserved if you got a
bunch of coins you can lose some you can
melt them you can eat them you can you
can just you can counterfeit your new
money print new bills and so on this is
all allowed but it's very handy to have
a system in which we pretend that money
is also conserved and we we shouldn't
throw it away we shouldn't print our own
and we should pay back our debts to try
to eliminate them and all this becomes
part of the narrative of money over time
and we almost take it for granted today
until we come to the point where we
eliminated things like the gold standard
of money where we had physical physical
measurements of money and you had you
then ask the question where does money
come from and in the marxist sense
there's a narrative we you know we still
use this phrase we need to make money
and we imagine people working in our
mind and digging up something and this
turns magically into money and of course
it doesn't in a world in which money is
simply a bunch of notes and exchanged
media that you have to get your hands on
in order to pay for things if you're
just exchanging goods yes okay you can
exchange and barter with those goods
that you've worked for but in the world
of virtualized money in which it becomes
this kind of network layer you actually
need to get hold of that networking
material that medium of money
and the only way we could do that now is
through banks banks are the initiator of
money and money is created through debt
so you don't get given money for digging
a coal or growing wheats you have to go
to the bank and say I'd like to borrow
some money and they will give you money
that you can spend in return for paying
it back later and all of the other stuff
that bartering and the trading and the
exchanging you could've do in your own
time the money takes on a story of its
own but this is kind of interesting
because so first of all to to get money
that means you need a bank account and
even today there's a whole there are all
swathe as a population around the world
which where people are unable to get
into the banking system because they're
not credit worthy they come from the
wrong caste they that are wrong color
they live in the wrong part of town and
so on you're not part of the club with
the secret handshake you need a way into
that system so that's the first part it
becomes a social network and potentially
a closed one and then once you've
managed to get money from the bank or
whatever you create this debt that debt
actually carries with it more
information than the money that they
give you in return so in order to get
that money you may have to give up
details personal details your credit
history how trustworthy were you in the
past and they keep this information and
that of course spreads through their
private network so even after you've
paid back the money which you think
might have annihilate the debt in the
sense that particles and antiparticles
maeín I like one another in physics you
may not completely annihilate your debt
because the memory of all of all the
semantics the memory of that history
follows you around and so this this
ledger of transactions that follows you
around in the world as you go becomes a
kind of almost like you know in physics
we talk about this virtual cloud that
hangs around bare particles in in
monetary terms we have this
cloud of foreboding which is our credit
history if you will that fellas around
us around as well and that of course may
influence transactions in the future so
data and money superficially seem to be
the opposite of one another but in fact
deaths carries with it memories that are
far more complex and networks than the
money itself very very good point one of
the key attributes of debt is interest
what is it and what's the rationale for
it yeah interest is one of those complex
things that I I always find it extremely
hard to understand and going back in
history it's even we've been through you
know epochs in which interest was banned
forbidden in the Islamic banking system
it's still forbidden in principle
interest is this idea that when you
borrow money that's a service and you
should perhaps pay for that service so
you have a service fee you have to pay a
certain amount for the to compensate the
lender which is kind of absurd in a
sense because you know it didn't cost
thanks anything to create the money
especially in the modern system right
there no you're not doing them out of
anything by by borrowing the money in
fact quite the contrary but we've we've
taken on this narrative of interest as a
form of compensation for the money being
unavailable to somebody else so we
should pay them for that service for
that so the privilege of how of handling
the money so that's one one version of
of what interest is another one is that
you know the interest rate that we hear
about on the news is quite a confusing
beast it's only vaguely related to the
the rate of interest we pay on our
mortgages which may or may not be a
service fee or whatever but that makes
economics pretty difficult for ordinary
folks to understand and a highly
illusory game even for bankers to
understand what they're trying to do is
to try to incorporate projections for
what money might be worth
in the future if I hold on to a bunch of
money instead of passing it on to
somebody else what happens if the buying
power that money the purchasing power of
that money is less because I'm holding
on to it because prices are rising then
by holding on to that money I may be
losing or winning depending on whether
the prices are going up or down so I may
I may need to be compensated for that
loss so the fact that in any kind of
world of processes processes are always
racing one another in time you know is
one process becoming more expensive than
another will we have to pay more for
anything going at a faster rate than the
growth of the thing that we're hanging
on to will I be able to catch the train
you know if I run fast enough do I have
to borrow money in order to catch my
train this idea of racing processes is
also present in money so if we loan
money to to pay for a house but the
house prices increased before we pay for
it we've already you know lost somehow
so there's this rule this concept in
which interest is also part of playing
with time and space and for transactions
there as well
and we're trying to compensate perhaps
people holding lots of money or people
who've lent money for what it could have
been what they could have done with it
had they had the money themselves and
again this goes back to this notion that
money is imagined to be a conserved
quantity in which you know if I have it
you can't have it and so on it's not
really true but it's the game that we
play in a strange kind of quite we buy
strange rules if we we play it by rules
that people make up as they go along but
but that's sort of part of the rationale
about how you try to motivate people to
pay you back the money that you lent
them okay very good I will add you
basically laid out two rationales for
interest one is time value of money as a
commodity and the second is currency
risk as I extracted what you were saying
but there is of course a third one about
real interest rates which is default
risk
so while that does not apply to
so-called risk-free monies for instance
perhaps maybe not anymore
government bonds in the real world we
like when we purchase a car as you
talked about before our credit history
will modify quite significantly the
interest rate we actually pay I just
want to make that point for the listener
now let me ask you one of these crazy
questions that money nerds always ask
each other and scratch their head a bit
love to hear your answer one of the
conundrums of bank interest money is
that the money is created at the bank
for the principal but not for the
interest what does that mean what
implications does that have for the
financial system I'm not sure I
understand the question you okay so
let's say I'm a you know I I buy a house
I borrow from a hundred thousand from
the bank buy the house that hundred
thousand flows to the Builder and off to
his workers etc but I'm now on the hook
to pay five percent annual interest no
money was created in the system to pay
that interest could it some people say
that this is a crazed treadmill which
means that if the banking system isn't
growing
it'll catastrophic Li collapse love to
know your take on that seeming anomaly
yes so this is the the paradox of money
and the assumption the money is
conserved if you if you borrow 10 10
bucks and you have to pay back more than
that then where does that money come
from to pay back more than you actually
borrowed if the money had to be created
by debt in the first place so how do you
get more money back for what you were
then then what you initially were to be
able to pay back the interest let me hop
in and say here say I'm a little
interested in what it means to me as the
borrower but I'm more interested in the
systematics you know the fact that the
total sum of payments is now greater
than the sum of money in the system yeah
I understand and that's what I'm getting
to that so ok so right so you know if if
everyone's borrowing money and they all
have to pay it back how can there be
more money in the system to pay it back
then there was created by the banks in
the first place well one one answer to
that also
could be related to a phenomenon physics
called renormalization where over time
the value of money and I hate that we'll
come back to talk about that in a bit
perhaps the value of money what its
purchasing power is changes because
prices are rising so because prices rise
we have to pump more money into the
system to be able to pay for things and
and of course there's more people on the
planet are born more money has to be
created for them to buy things as well
so there is a need for more and more
money all the time and that means people
have to be borrowing more and more money
over time so it seems to make no sense
it seems like we would be in permanent
debt and of course we are in permanent
debt all of the time but the fact that
prices are rising and you can be paid
back more leads to the concept of
inflation which allows you to get back
more money than you perhaps paid for
something and make profit and that
margin assuming that it's always racing
the creation of money and doing
reasonably well and you don't care too
much about the debt you can try to make
that game work in such a way that you're
paying back your debts as somebody else
is borrowing kind of on your behalf
somewhere else in the world and the
network effect of that is routing money
to you at just the right way that you're
pushing death away from you all of the
time but of course new debt is being
created all of the time at the edge
which is never been paid back and so
there's this kind of pyramid game
ongoing and our our economic story
around profit and interests and so on is
essentially a gigantic pyramid scheme in
which debt is continuously being created
devalued and the semantics of it being
scattered around like entropy so that we
don't care about it anymore in order to
continue to play and it's I mean it
scares the heck out of me I don't know
about anyone else but when I look at the
way the financial system works
it's amazing to me every single day
that it can possibly work and yet it
seems to have periods of stability and
instability of course but but it seems
to sometimes
yeah and it's sort of where I call it
metastable right kind of like when
you're running a human running is
actually falling right it's a controlled
fall yes and sometimes when you're
running your foot hits a curb or you
step on a toy some kid left on the
sidewalk dad you go on your face right I
think of our financial system as that as
our Monday a monetary and financial
system is that a controlled running fall
which mostly works but sometimes you
fall down and sometimes you fall down
hard enough to break your noggin now you
talked about inflation and interest we
are now have been really since 2008 in a
very strange world where from time to
time deflation has raised its head in
Japan basically it's been in deflation
or close to it for the last 20 years and
deflation is flickered on and off in
Europe and terrified the hell out of the
central bankers also more peculiarly in
your book you talk about negative
interest rate but you noted as more of a
historical curiosity today it's reality
for the last several years there's been
negative interest rates on short and
even medium term bonds from Switzerland
Germany Japan several other countries
I've checked yesterday and the Swiss
rate I think on three-year bills is now
minus 0.8 percent and Germany it's about
0.5% I understand I haven't done the
research to confirm if I understand in
Europe some of the triple-a rated
corporate bonds are now mildly negative
on their interest rates what does a
world of deflation and negative interest
rates indicate to us about money and how
did your theory of money even account
for that yeah this is a huge topic and
you're absolutely right negative
interest rates are now pervasive in
Japan and Europe and the eurozone in
particular I have to say I'm not an
expert on you firstly I'm not an
economist by any means one of the
interesting books that got me interested
in the question of money in the
beginning was first of all Yanis
varoufakis books the first one was and
the weeks are for what they must which
was about the Greek debt crisis in
Europe
and then his later is at you in his
earlier book but I read that afterwards
called the global miner tour which is
about the financial crisis and the
monetary system and then after that I
stumbled across a an interview with
Steve Kean Australian economist who
wrote this fabulous book called
debunking economics he's a he belongs to
the Church of Minsky I'm in Minsky and
his death models Minsky wrote a book
called stabilizing an unstable economy
and can it happen again
around these these various deflationary
episodes and these financial crises that
seem to recur every 10 years or so the
mother of all being the one in two
thousand seven and eight and they they
have models for for describing these
these scenarios which go far beyond the
kind of monetary modeling that I've
undertaken using promise theory they use
these differential rate based models you
know based on average statistical
measures and the econometrics that
economists use like interest rates and
GDP and so on which allow you to model
money on the timescale of decades and
years and over long periods of time of
course they then try to apply them to
money markets on the scale of days and
weeks and months which is kind of absurd
and leads to this meta stability that
you were just talking about and this
this is I find this sort of
extraordinary because this got me
interested in the concept of money and
whether or not that network of effects
could work on the timescale of those
microscopic interactions so my promise
theory money is really a microscopic
view of money if you will it's a
transactional view at the level of our
everyday payments for things the trust
incurred in the relationships between us
you know what allows that one person to
pay for something and what will make
your client be willing to pay you for
your services how do those relationships
get started in order to bootstrap that
whole motor owned machine engine of the
world I think that's what Iran called it
the engine of the world
and that engine of the worldview is what
the macro economists like to study and
to model and talk about that macroscopic
version of money is a totally different
beast than the microscopic version that
we were talking about in terms of
transactions and this was this began to
I think people began to realize this
after the you know the original
depression during the 30s where Keynes
became you know John Maynard Keynes the
British economist became a force of
nature or force of economics if you will
talking about the role of debt and the
fact that this the way in which banks
create money was an important thing that
had to be taken into account because it
may seem bizarre for for our readers to
to hear that economist economists
economics didn't model money and and to
this day many economists talk about
economics GDP and debt and interest
rates and unemployment without ever
referring to to money as a as a medium
and what it does this is quite
extraordinary and Steve Kean makes a big
point of this in his book which I found
very illuminating inspired me to try to
get to the bottom of what money was all
about what these guys do is they they
look at these global indicators like GDP
unemployment and they use kind of
straight line or polynomial
relationships between them simple
deterministic laws bit like the laws of
physics that you know he was alluding to
before going back to this time when
economists wanted economics to be like
the laws of physics and I have this
physics Envy you just solve it in your
differential equation subject to some
boundary conditions and then you predict
next year's economy and people still do
this with these Goodwin Minsky models
that are used in various degrees of
approximation to try to look at the
trends that are ongoing
but this to me from a promise Theory
perspective this goes back to something
which I call the principle of separation
of scales which with your background in
complexity science you you recognize as
well has been one of the most important
things of complex systems house how
systems exist on different scales and
they make different promises at each
different scale so there is an
interaction story at each identifiable
or separable scale of a system which
tells a story of its own and those
stories are not necessarily clearly
related or in a simple way related and
of course this means that he called
economics and the story of money and the
story of society that it tells is not
like one simple story it's a story on
many levels
economists separate themselves into
micro economists macro economists see
there should probably be meso economists
in there as well
but I never heard of them before but I
think him economics is attempting to go
through a revolution to reinvent itself
along these lines and some of those
advocates like Minsky was an early one
largely forgotten today Keynes cost
widely misrepresented in his his version
of events is his theory was kind of
hijacked by the neoclassical economists
and misrepresented for many years and
then sort of the modern advocates like
Yanis varoufakis and Steve Kean and even
old guys like Shiller the Nobel Prize
winner his latest books on narrative
economics and so on indicating how we we
try to separate the the storylines of
the different scales in the economy to
to predict how stuff happens so you know
long and rambling answer to you to your
question really economics being a
complex system is is a complex thing to
describe many different scales and we
have to have different stories about it
at each of these scales the nature and
characteristics of those stories at
different scales are course very
different
absolutely very good perspective I will
second the call-out the Steve Keynes
economics debunked which is a must read
if you want to understand why our
Economist's have led us so far astray
I've got Schiller's narrative economics
on my soon to be read stack and another
one I'd call out and this is actually my
touchstone in my own work in monetary
theory the money illusion by Irving
Fisher very I kind of classic economist
back in the 20s and 30s who I still
believe saw money more accurately than
anybody else and finally if you want to
see the ruddy in view about money I do
have a talk on the internet type in
dividend money gym rut on YouTube and
you will see my 90-minute talk about an
alternative money system that doesn't
require debt let's move on another thing
that you've talked about in your book
and some considerable detail something
that frankly right at the edge of my
understanding of money and one of the
things that makes us so damn complicated
is how foreign exchange changes our
analysis on money could you talk to us a
little bit about foreign exchange and
how that couples to any given country's
monetary system so we start with this
idea the banks create money and each
sovereign realm with its own banking
system can create money of its own in
fact you are I could tomorrow just
create our own currency right off the
bat if we wanted to anyone is free to do
that at any time companies do it from
time to time we have coffee cards and
flight miles and and so on these loyalty
systems that people create and of course
there are many reasons for doing this
but let's not get into that right now
the trick of creating your own money is
to get people to accept it alright so if
someone will agree to use your currency
and give it back to such a degree that
it forms a network then it starts to
become a useful thing so it's like if
you're on the internet if you have a
bunch of internet packets TCP packets
but no one else supports TCP you're
stuck you know you you're not going
anywhere
but if the whole world adopts tcp/ip
then suddenly you've got an Internet and
in a similar way you would like to have
a global currency in which everybody
could pay everyone else and you could
make you could just sell things and buy
things freely but because of the
relationship to politics not everyone
really wants to do that because who gets
to decide how much money is in
circulation will affect how well-off
people will be which is a political
issue you know who gets to borrow money
and if some people start getting too
rich
how will we control that so there's
there's a lever of control which is
implicit in money which is highly
political in and of course governments
and and banks even and private
corporations want to be able to control
that to some extent so sovereignty over
money and its control is an important
thing and so after the Second World War
the Marshall Plan and all of the
enormous war costs that reparations had
to be made Keynes apparently proposed
the idea of a global currency but this
was actually brought down by Washington
because Washington wanted to have an
advantage over the rest of the world to
control certain resources like the oil
and so on for political gains and still
maintains that control lever which
allows you to perform sanctions on
countries and so on so this political
dimension means that that the national
boundaries of countries now play a role
in currencies and exchanging money if
you want to pay for something in another
country you have to go through this
rather complex dance buy of buying
currency using your own currency now how
does that work if you if money is
created only in the foreign country and
you you could only get money from by
paying in your own currency and it
doesn't work in the other country how's
that gonna work well of course what
happens is that each country basically
has bank accounts in each other's banks
like the foreign banks have bank
accounts in one another's banks and they
will issue debt
in order to issue currency in in the in
the foreign currency so again it's a
game of virtual debt floating around
with bonds and other instruments we
don't have to get into the details are
if if I even understood you know a
fraction of it but it's basically the
the technology of deaths and ledges
creating debt and instantiating money in
the currency required but then of course
there's another story around what is
that money worth in terms of what you
can buy for it and the the basic rule I
think which is easy to understand for
everyone is that money is worth exactly
as much as you can get for it now you
offer somebody a dollar you make it
bubble gum you make it a car it just
depends how what people are feeling on
the day so there's a trust aspect to
that there's also a market-based aspect
of that if I can get something from
somebody else cheaper than your prices
fluctuate does a whole language of
prices which is a story unto itself but
that means that the effective purchasing
power of money what we like to call the
value of money is a highly relativistic
highly fickle and mercurial aspect of
global communication which is constantly
fluctuating and it means that money we
thought we had can just vanish overnight
because markets are suddenly taking
different rates of money for something
this happened to friends of mine who
borrowed money from one bank in one
currency or ordered something online in
one currency and then the order was
cancelled and they were paid back or
refunded the amount but the amount was
either less or more in the interim than
what they paid for it originally so he
could either make a profit or a loss
just by canceling an order which is one
of those extraordinary uncertainties in
in the modern world but this this is
again all part of this promise theoretic
story in which you have independent
agents in this case the national
sovereignties or the central bank's
actually the private banks
each maintaining their own version of
money their own rates of interest and
their own rules essentially about how to
repay that and that the semantics of all
of that impinge upon the effective
amount of money that people have in
their accounts over time and of course
it manifests itself in some interesting
ways for the individual small-scale for
an exchange can be horrendously
expensive you go to those goddamn money
things at the airport where they hit you
eight or ten percent and if you were a
let's say an economic migrant a
third-world person working in the first
world to get your remittance back to
your family could be more than that yep
part of the system that has not somehow
evolved to be very efficient one of the
things that we've talked about a little
bit is the supply of money one of the
things that I don't think was in your
book too much and unfortunately you
don't have a kindle edition so I
couldn't search and see is the velocity
of money have you thought a little bit
about how the quantity and supply of
money interact so this concept of the
velocity of money is how quickly in some
sense money is changing hands and it's
you know under like velocity in in the
Newtonian sense of physics it's not a
simple simple concept it can be
discussed as a statistical concept on
the scale of these macroeconomic models
but the meaning of that thing I think is
a bit iffy I don't I wouldn't place too
much sway in that concept bill I don't
know what macro economist would say
about it personally to me it doesn't to
make too much sense for the simple
reason that you or I operate with money
only on the scale of agents and
transactions not in these statistical
averages over time but what's important
about this concept of how fast money
moves is that if money pools in places
you know if you somebody hoards money
for two for too long the supply of money
is effectively stunted for other people
you need a certain amount of money
flowing in order to be able to buy stuff
and if somebody's stashed you know 90%
of the money in
their bank account then it means that
only 10% of the money are available for
the rest of the world to buy stuff which
may not be enough what they need to do
so you then need to borrow more so it's
important that money maintains this sort
of fluidity or liquidity as they say in
economics it keeps moving it doesn't
stay still for too long now this is kind
of our odds with the idea that you want
to accumulate buffers of money in order
to perform these extraordinary acts of
building or borrowing to to overcome
obstacles and barriers along the way
this is a kind of the the discussion if
you like the the difference between the
Western debt based economics that is
popular in America and Britain and the
German version of monetary economics in
which you're supposed to save up in
advance you know you're good savers
putting away for a rainy day and you
never take on too much debt you pay back
your debts this has been studied at
great length in David Gruber's book
again and not only his book but Thomas
Picard his book on capital which I liked
very much you know he studies the
history of debt and lending and
borrowing and whether or not you know
having huge debts instead of stockpiling
money over time is in any way good or
bad for you and I think by studying the
records in especially in Britain and
France who have kept records longer than
many other countries he he kind of
concludes that debt is not all that bad
as it's not as bad as we think it is and
this kind of German model of you'd
better save up your pennies in your
piggy bank if you want to afford
something rather than borrowing is
actually false that is more or less
harmless over time because of inflation
and if you don't lose your cool it can
be the better way perhaps of overcoming
financial obstacles rather than
trying to stop money from flowing so in
a whereas you know we Europeans look at
you Americans as big spenders going into
debt maxing out credit cards is being
sort of wow this is sort of shocking to
you to a European mentality in the long
run it perhaps it doesn't really matter
and that might actually be the way to
get ahead in in the financial system
such as it is so this is a pretty
interesting issue which I have a small
understanding of but I think it it's
based around you know the level I
understand it it's based around the
individual agents and their willingness
to accumulate money and pass it on
depending on their own private policies
and it's interesting spent a secular
downward trend in velocity in the US for
instance I just pulled up the Federal
Reserve velocity of m2 money stock in
1996 kind of been the hot economy the
velocity of money was about 2.2 meaning
that the typical dollar was spent twice
in a year it's currently down around 1.4
and of course what that is is that money
times velocity equals GDP it's
essentially a derived function so GDP
continues to grow money supply has grown
tremendously with the various qyz etc
during the financial crisis we now have
a much bigger money supply than we used
to and the GDP has been growing
relatively slowly and so algebraically
the velocity has to have come down which
basically means people are sitting on
money more or money is stuck in places
where it can't do anything this is
something you hear from bankers that
well we got money in our lending
capacity but there really isn't as much
demand for lending as there used to be
at least creditworthy lending that's an
interesting phenomena that we're in yeah
and Jim this comes back to your point
about the negative interest rates again
and the negative interest rate is an
incentive for people to not hold on to
money if you've got money in the bank
you're actually being charged now for
having it there rather than being
offered a premium for for keeping it
there
and so the negative interest rates are a
way of trying to kick people at the ass
and get them to spend the money a little
bit and lend them money in order to get
the money moving around the system again
I think in terms of designing
alternative money systems there's a
concept called de Mirage which is a
charge for storing money and of course
it goes way back to the days when gold
was money and people would have gold
notes that they'd get from their bankers
but at the same time the bank would
charge you a fee to hold your money and
one can imagine that in a you know a new
cryptocurrency or other kind of cyber
currency where you could actually have a
negative interest rate built into the
system even though money may not come
from actual debt you can actually have a
charge to encourage people to move it
you could indeed adjust that Demma raj
to either speed up or slow down the
money I think however you organize your
economy whether it's you know a
cryptocurrency with a maximum amount of
Bitcoin or whatever you're not an upper
limit on that whether you allow money to
grow without without limit as in
Zimbabwe oh you know with the
extraordinary inflation rates there's
this multi scale aspect of money which
you're never going to escape one way or
another which is that the the long-term
trends of spending GDP interest rates
and all the mechanisms the levers which
people use to encourage to manipulate to
motivate us to interact with one another
those long scale things act as a kind of
a boundary condition in forming thus the
much faster transactions that apply to
us in our daily lives and so they they
affect the rate in which we are allowed
to borrow money in other words the rate
at which we can now acquire money to
solve problems and so there's this
feedback system between the bankers and
the world of finance here's which who
are dealing with things like GDP which
is an utterly meaningless concept to to
most of us the interest rates that we
hear on the news again utterly
meaningless concepts to most of us
and then the way they get turned into
decisions made at your local bank for
how much it's gonna cost you to pay your
mortgage this week and whether or not
you can afford to buy you know food at
the supermarket or whatever so this this
feedback system is a multiscale feedback
system which makes it a complex system
and it's poorly understood and as you
say metastable for that reason let's
think of a couple little more technical
areas that you had some very interesting
things to say about the entropy of
network money and how we think about
that what does it mean entropy is one of
those concepts I wanna say to when
people bring it up because it's it's
something people love to pull the wool
over other's eyes with john von Lohmann
even made that point I think to Claude
Shannon back in the day of he was
working on communications theory if you
call it entropy no one will understand
what you're talking about but entropy is
it's essentially a measure of how
distributed something is in a system if
everyone has exactly the same amount of
something you say the entropy of that
thing ism is maximal so if we all have
the same amount of money the entropy of
money would be maximal if if we all have
the same amount of wheat the entropy of
wheat would be maximum the minimum
amount of entropy is sort of the
opposite of that where one person has
all of it and no one has nobody else has
any and this is obviously important for
trade and transactions because if we all
have the same amount of something then
we've got no incentive to trade anything
so we definitely don't want to end up in
a situation of maximum entropy in money
economics commodities or whatever
similarly we don't want one person to
have everything because then it would
just be a charity show and you'd be
getting handouts from somebody who is
basically the ruler so this is concept
much in physics about how entropy
represents the motor of the system if if
a system has reached maximum entropy the
system ain't going round
nothing's gonna happen so we're trying
to avoid that from happening and one of
the antidotes to that happening is is
exactly the banking system where banks
can create new money in order to create
a surplus of purchasing power and then
of course we need entrepreneurs and
companies to create surpluses of goods
here and there to prevent the heat death
or the wheats death of the universe and
that's that kind of score so it's a
little bit related to this concept of
velocity of money it's a very broad
concept a theoretical concept if you
like not too useful and we certainly
hope that we never get to the point
where entropy becomes a useful measure
it would be a sort of let's just say the
heat death of the economic system and it
is interesting even though I do
criticize the fractional reserve banking
style of money one of the things it does
do is it forces the circulation right
because typically loans are for
relatively short periods of time I think
the average about four or five years and
so money comes into the banks is
destroyed literally when you repay
principal on a loan the money is
destroyed and then the bank typically
lends it back out creating new money and
that money then diffuses back out into
the system so we essentially have a
circular flow of money out to loans back
to the bank and then back out again
which does provide a fairly strong force
away from entropy right and the pump we
didn't talk about earlier is the bank's
conscious create any amount of money
anymore there there are limits on
deposits that they have to hold in order
to create new money by regulation this
is simply a convention it's not a law of
nature but it's a legal convention I
guess in different countries and they
can adjust it for political or economic
purposes yeah let's go into some stuff
that maybe gets a little closer to
easily understood promise theory and
that's the idea of payments there's lots
of different ways that things can be
paid and interestingly payments have
attributes that aren't necessarily
obvious on the surface for instance
despite all these fancy bitcoins and
this and that credit cards still have a
big role to play in the economy frankly
I always pay
for anything I can with a high-end
credit card like an American Express
because it has a special attribute of
renunciation right American Express
since I've been a customer for 50 years
or something 40 years trust me when I
say take the money back from that
asshole right the goods they gave was no
damn good
and they'll just do it American Express
will just take the money back from the
vendor talk about payments and how that
whole thing works and how it's much more
nuanced than it appears on the surface
yes this is incredibly interesting
points especially in this world of
bitcoins and cryptocurrencies that have
taken off on the idea of mistrusting the
banking system the concept of money as a
fungible Network packet layer of
communication is pretty important and in
order to carry out that function you
should have as few labels as few
semantics as possible just as in the
internet you want the IP layer or the
tcp/ip layer to be that very relatively
few markers and labels and and things
that identify it you don't want money to
be tied to a particular person because
you want it to flow between people you
don't want it to be specific to a
particular kind of good you know you can
only use this money for wheat even
though we create many of these loyalty
systems now like air miles and and
coffee cards can only be redeemed with
certain suppliers and so on these are
these are ways of playing games with
with trust by adding labels to money to
bring people back and to sort of
maintain relationships by encouraging
with incentives people to come back to
and maintain the same relationships
rather than allowing money to flow
freely and diffuse without opinion if
you will and part of this of course
happens with banks as well although when
you have a national currency like like
the dollar or the pound or the euro
which works within a certain sovereign
realm the money kind of is tied to the
central bank and then you have foreign
exchanges as we discussed before but if
you ever begin to mistrust the role of
that intermediary the money itself or
the third party that you go through like
a bank that maintains a ledger for you
to pay on it could be your credit card
or your simply your your checking
account or whatever then you may want to
try to go back to this concept of Botto
individual handing over the goods
directly again but by doing so you would
lose a lot of value all of those things
we discussed previously about the time
the ability to play with time the
ability to rescind your your payment as
you mentioned you know I regret that
decision please take it back all those
things become impossible in a world in
which you don't have some kind of
service layer in the middle so these
trusted third parties like the banks and
the credit card companies while at one
point being able to have considerable
power as network hubs as exchange hubs
within whatever currency they belong to
they also are able to provide smart
services like lending like rescinding
money like tracing certain transactions
and you know they even can perform
services for the police to be able to
track money laundering and things like
this although they don't do a terribly
good job on that the argument that came
up after the 2008 crash that led to
Bitcoin and the cryptocurrencies was
well these these banks because of their
games with lending and refinancing of
loans and monetary instrumentation has
gone wild they've lost control of
themselves they now wield too much power
over ordinary people let's claim back
trust by taking away that need to trust
the middleman
of course that's entirely misplaced
because you're still trusting a
middleman there is still a middleman in
in the cryptocurrencies it's now a
software system instead of a banking
entity so it may be slightly more
predictable in some senses but not in
others because it's still a market
making it work and it's still
fluctuating based on the weather of who
happens to be running Bitcoin mining
operations at the time so it's very very
complicated picture but this ability to
put services in between is extremely
analogous to this OSI model of
networking layers from the bottom most
layers of transport to the top most
layers of smart services that we expect
from the web but you gotta be careful
about where you put different functions
on the different layers of the network
stack so should we put you know should
we have smart dollar bills would that be
good could we add labels to the money
well no you're not allowed to write on
the bills so we're not allowed to add
money there that's good okay that means
money is still fungible but then that
prevents you from creating loyalty
points and and creating customer value
through additional services that you
could provide so we want to be able to
add those things at a higher level of
abstraction and this is a role of the
banks and the money handle is that I
think has been greatly underestimated in
the West in China people are very good
at doing this they've come far further
than us in in the Western world by
adding these smart services to money
taking a promise Theory perspective as
you mentioned the beginning okay so in
promise theory you have agents and you
have the promises promises and money--i
promises and the proxies that carry
those promises the the network packets
if you like of the bills and the the
trusted third parties the network hubs
like the banks but then what about the
end agents the agents at the end if you
put your intelligence into those
guys like it used to be in the world of
bartering you could say well I'm gonna
put all of my smart services into the
end points instead the pricing how is
the service offered what what is
included in the price is it just a
number how much you're willing to pay or
in other is it a form to fill out you
know do I have to give you additional
information do I have to will I add some
extra stuff coming back to you as a
service alongside this this is kind of
interesting we're starting to see banks
realizing they've been caught with their
pants down here because they are network
hubs at the center of this vast network
technology that is money and they could
be exploiting that hub advantage to
provide additional services like
authentication of users you know your
identity is essentially your bank
account ID right in my home country
Scandinavia in Norway the banks have
taken on this role of validating or
authenticating users for the government
now so we see banks as third-party
network providers starting to realize
they have other services they can offer
them simply routing money they can route
other kinds of information to they're in
a great position to do that
but no one is quite sure how to go about
this at the moment and receive all kinds
of inconsistent schemes except in China
where there's been far greater
homogeneous Asian and willingness to
interact and innovate around this space
so you know those guys in China have
their social media platform WeChat and
the Ali Baba's payment system and they
use those they they interact and you can
lend money you can borrow money just
through your phone app at the push of a
button in a very simple way and all of
these financial services easily
available they're tied in to other
network services like facial recognition
so you go to the supermarket
walk out and it'll see your face and you
pay pay with your face
so all of these possibilities can be
embedded within the network architecture
that is money the question is where do
we want to put it in the money packets
in the pricing at the edge points in the
agents or in the network transactions
mmm that's good we're getting a little
late on time so I'm going to skip over
some more details about our current
money system that there from your book
I'd encourage the listeners to read the
book they're interested on those details
let's talk about the wild new world of
new money's though actually before we do
that sounds like you know fair amount
about these Chinese payment systems
which I do not are those payment systems
using banks as intermediaries but just
doing so efficiently and quickly or is
there near money or something else
that's just outside the banking system
there yeah this is a very interesting it
was a great question in the beginning
Alibaba and WeChat had monetary systems
completely outside the banking world so
compare them to the airlines and the
systems of air miles that you can use to
buy with in the airline networks you
know an Allen has so many resources it
has such huge buffers of money and it's
into every kind of commodity you can
imagine it needs transportation oil fuel
it could be its own it is basically its
own virtual sovereignty and it's able to
manage huge pools of money and debt
simply within that framework without
involving banks at all and in a similar
way these massive companies the
extraordinary success of Alibaba and
WeChat and to enable them to create
their own essentially their own virtual
money and they could do this completely
outside the normal banking system but
then the bank's caught wind of this and
didn't like it and and even fought back
and eventually the government had to
prevent them from sort of tie it all
together in one consistent system so
keeping the banks in the loop in order
to stabilize the economy without letting
the bank's collapse essentially and also
they need to be able do it for macro
purposes
you know control money supply and
velocity I suspect so now these days is
Alibaba we shad have their own banks
essentially so they can get the kind of
speed and low cost they need they are
banks themselves you and I think yeah
let's step over to the next topic I'm
sure our listeners have been waiting for
it is your thoughts on crypto currencies
let's start with Bitcoin and the claim
that is a trustless system
yeah premise theory basically puts a
hammer on the head to that idea there's
no such thing as a trustless system you
can only move trust around because money
is a promise it's a promise to redeem a
value in the future it's a time promise
you know using this token I will give
you something in return at a later time
if that promise fails to be kept you
would lose trust in the money so
regardless of whether you're using
Bitcoin dollars yours whatever you need
to trust the money now what do you mean
my money is it a trusted third party
like a bank ledger checking account a
Visa account PayPal Alibaba whatever it
is there is some intermediary whether
it's a peer-to-peer network of
libertarians that want to reclaim
sovereignty of the monetary system by
melting polar ice caps or do we simply
pay a company to do it for us on our
behalf and trust them
the key fact that I think they got wrong
in this essentially libertarian view of
the economy is that you can't get away
with not having trust Trust is the very
glue of society if you lose trust in
your third parties your institutions
that makes the glue society together if
you lose trust in your network
you've lost society itself you you start
to fragment off into you different
trenches and you start firing at each
other instead of cooperating so Trust is
the glue of cooperation you can't do
without it
now all these cryptocurrencies do is
they replace trust in the banks and I am
a centralized service with trust in a
decentralized service and
of software which is presumably
certified which nobody verifies or
validates even if they have the ability
in principle to do it because of
open-source and that they they serve no
function that cannot equally be served
by regulation we don't have a way of
running society without government in
the modern world throughout history have
only been two examples that I know of of
government lists societies one one was
you know centuries ago in the Niger
Delta northern Africa and one was in
Middle China in antiquity but in the
modern world we've always built
societies around central seeds that that
allow us to root our trust through
intermediaries and it goes back to the
ability to scale society you know
society began with kinship family
relations you know anyone not in your
tribe you fight against you you it's
either us or them one of your previous
speakers talked about hobbits and
hooligans and Vulcans you know if you're
not uh if you're not in my tribe you're
in another tribe I'm gonna hate you
because you're in the other tribe and
that's an unstable situation on which to
build trade and Trust and society and
larger scale cooperation so if you're on
a scale cooperation you want to move
away from kinship from tribal relations
to these impartial organs which are the
foundations of modern society the banks
the institutions of government and so on
and this depersonalization of society is
the thing that allowed us to scale it so
if we're going to retreat from that
position by saying I no longer want to
trust those institutions then we will
retreat from the model of society we
have today this was he mentioned the
beginning one of the fiction books that
I wrote many years ago a book called
slogans I I said I've anticipated this
back in 2002 or three or something that
our electronic devices are handheld what
today our smartphones
didn't exist at the time I read the book
but the smartphone's essentially allow
us to have what we wanted the push of a
button without having to interact
closely with with bartering opponents so
we have no knowledge of them no know
dunbar relationship between them on
which we know them at the level of our
friends to be trustworthy and that means
these impersonal channels of
communication the ability to mail order
erode the fabric of trust on which
society is built you can see it as you
walk down the street and there are
people or not people don't tip their
hats to each other anymore maybe quite
the opposite you know so this is
potential risk I believe in society in
the way that it works today that we may
lose our sense of society if we're not
careful by introducing too many of these
go-betweens that appear to eliminate the
need to know your opponents and trust
them very interesting perspective you
also did mention melting the polar ice
caps I have a good friend who describes
Bitcoin as accelerating the heat death
of the universe you know the same idea
him and probably to know good point as
you described on the other hand the
other big thrust of innovation in crypto
currencies I find much more interesting
and that's the smart contracts that sit
on top of aetherium in fact when I was
reading your first book on promise
theory from C's and applications I think
we'll figure it out we'll put it on the
website
anyway when I was reading that book I
said damn smart contracts would be a
very interesting way to formally create
some of these promises you were talking
about do you have any thoughts on how
things like smart contract systems map
onto your promise theory yeah I also got
interested in this this question in
until again I realized that the the cost
of it all I mean first of all smart
contracts a great idea so then you're
putting some of the intelligence in the
trusted third party and in this case the
trusted third party is a mobile
entity which were decentralized entity
rather than a centralized one like a
bank there's no reason why you couldn't
have smart contracts in a bank a regular
bank right so there's nothing specific
about cryptocurrencies that makes them
able to do or blockchain I should say
that enables it to perform these smart
services that couldn't be done with
centralized services equally well and
much cheaper and much faster to mention
something else but this yes you're
absolutely right so smart contracts
absolutely powerful concept how much
intelligence do you want to put into the
machinery of the network itself there's
a story around this which goes if we go
to Internet technologies now the the
corresponding thing in the world of
Cisco and Huawei and the network
providers these guys had an idea when
the cloud came along of something called
network function virtualization in which
all of those boxes essentially the
routers and the switches that we used to
route packets used to be just giant
boxes of metal which performed this
function in hardware they wanted to
replace all that using virtual machines
and to virtualize those functions in a
simple way and they called that network
function virtualization and they had a
very kind of poorly thought through idea
of what that would be just to replace
the rooters with virtual machines but
they missed an opportunity to see an
enormous an enormous opportunity there
in the ability to add smart functions
which we would now associate with things
like data pipelining smart
transformations of data coming in one
side going out the other in the similar
way smart transactions coming in with
certain amount of information and then
being turned into something else
enabling go-betweens like putting
certain payments in escrow so that you
can regret and reverse them as you could
do with your American Express cards we
talked about earlier so all of those
kind of smart functions edition
all services were dying to put those
into smart devices somewhere the
question is do you put them into the
money into the third parties or do you
have them in the edge in your smart
devices and in a way it depends a little
bit on where the information is and
where the data need to be in order to
maintain privacy restrictions and other
concerns of those of that kind of a
nature and also to be robust right yeah
you don't want all the brains to be in
your smartphone and all your data
suppose you drop it in the toilet you're
screwed right yeah absolutely I think
constantly use this I forget the name of
the episode but that old episode of Star
Trek where the whole of society ends up
worshiping this giant computer because
they've basically given their all of
their trusts of the machinery and they
no longer had no know how to do anything
by themselves this is what our
smartphones will eventually do to us
unless we you know take take steps to to
avoid that that kind of demise yeah
that's true now for our listeners who
have the entrepreneurial mindset mark
just handed you a multi-billion dollar
opportunity it's one I have mentioned to
people before I kill do a very small
amount of early-stage startup investing
for a while was getting way too many
blockchain Bitcoin cryptocurrency ideas
and I kept pushing back saying why does
this have to be on a blockchain and
seldom could anybody answer it so what
do you want to preneur should build a
smart contract infrastructure on top of
a single ledger or mildly distributed
high-speed ledger and push that out into
the world that would actually be useful
and when you get funding come and talk
to Jim and me and we'll join you as
advisors absolutely oh if I wasn't so
old and so rich I might do it myself but
let's leave that to the next generation
all right mark we're getting near to the
end point now what are some thoughts
that you might have for the future of
money if you know we are where we are
what could we expect to see next yeah
this is a simulation I wrote a little
bit about in the final chapter of the
book just speculating a little bit one
of the things that got me reading and
engaged in this was the story of devil
and this this realization in the world
of IT the developers and operations
people within a software team
communicate extremely poorly and tend to
throw stuff over the wall Tajik to each
other developers or write some software
thus the thread over the wall to the DT
operations people and say run this for
me
and then may get all the flack for it
you know when it goes wrong the users
come back and hit the operators and say
you know not you're not running this
properly you know when they get all the
blame
while the developers sit in their ivory
tower and take the money and this this
hasn't been going down well and it
hasn't been leading to much cooperation
so they realized that these two the dev
and the ops people needed to communicate
better form a dunbar relationship to one
another and get some proper cooperative
entanglement going between them and this
is a form of money it's a form of trust
building and this occurred to me that
this is a kind of currency that is
required in the world of work so in the
future of work in which we are more
distributed more and nuanced in our
functions in our roles I think it's safe
to say that we need to reinvent the
concept of money entirely to be smarter
and to deal with those ways of building
and maintaining trust now we've seen
this with the micro currencies things
like loyalty schemes airmiles for your
favorite airline or oneworld alliance or
whatever it is and we've seen it for you
know Starbucks and different coffee
houses and the and Amazon and so on this
the question of loyalty and Trust is
surfacing its ugly head because we have
neglected the role of trust in society
and I think people are starting to
realize just how important Trust is ask
any sales guy why they made their sales
quota and they'll say it was because we
have a relationship with the client it's
not because my pride
is best or because I have superior
technology it's because they trust you
enough to give you money and that's the
it's the foundation of business it's a
foundation of society without that glue
of trust our world will begin to unravel
and so for me that is the future of
money figuring out how to rekindle
trusts yeah I love it
my love you mentioned DevOps it's what
happens to be one of my pet things also
I was fortunate enough to be invited to
become chairman of the board of a
early-stage tech company in 2002 who
actually built the whole agile devops
philosophy into their business from the
get-go and man was that a different
world than at the world that you
described that I was used to in the 90s
where the developers would throw some
pile of over the wall people would
test that it would break and then the
developers would grudgingly fix it and
you know throw it over the wall two
weeks later and then the ops people
installing it doesn't work in DevOps
everything is built every day and it
really amazingly has changed the way
software development is done and in some
sense it's a way that Trust is used
scribe Dunbar level Trust has been able
to be built between the development the
operational community and for those of
you looking for a career young folks
DevOps is probably one of the hottest
tickets out there in our economy today
to your bigger vision of somehow using
money or money like systems to build
more trust in more ways I applaud that
tremendously trust is what holds our
society together after all if you have
anything to say to wrap up yeah how'd
you top that
that was a great ending soon thanks mark
for an amazingly interesting deep dive
into money I was wonderful to have you
on the show again and maybe at the
future we'll have you back and talk
about something else
well it's always great to come and chat
to you so I would love to do that any
time thanks Jim all right this has been
great thanks
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com